Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Certificates 1700-1991 PR 014
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of certificates
1700-1991
New-York Historical Society
PR 014
9.66 Linear feet in 9 boxes, 8 drawers of flat files
The New-York Historical Society Collection of Certificates (formerly known as the Certificate File) contains certificates from private and civic societies, clubs, and organizations. Diplomas, certificates of merit and various financial and legal documents are also included. The collection contains fine examples of engravings, lithographs, and typography.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Acquisition Note
The collection is made up of multiple purchases and gifts acquired over time.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society Collection of Certificates (formerly known as the Certificate File) spans the period from 1700 to 1991 and contains certificates issued by a wide variey of societies, clubs and organizations. Diplomas, certificates of merit and various financial and legal documents are included as well. The collection contains fine examples of engravings, lithographs, and typography.
The collection is divided into 22 series and arranged alphabetically by subject:
I: Art
II: Business
III: Celebrations and Events
IV: Civic
V: Education
VI: Financial
VII: Foreign Language
VIII: Fraternal
IX: Genealogical
X: Historical
XI: Humanitarian
XII: Legal
XIII: Medical
XIV: Memorial
XV: Military
XVI: Political and Government
XVII: Regional and Ethnic
XVIII: Religious
XIX: Scientific
XX: Sports and Athletics
XXI: Trades
XXII: Transportation
Accruals
This collection is open to new acquisitions.
Related Materials
N-YHS holds other certificates which can be found within manuscript collections, as well as certificates that were cataloged individually as manuscripts.
Associations, institutions, etc.; Charities.; Fraternal organizations.; Schools -- United States.; Societies.; Baptismal certificates.; Certificates.; Engravings (prints); Lithographs.; Marriage certificates.; Passports.; Stock certificates.; Typography.
- Series I: Art, 1816-1991
  Scope Note
  This series contains certificates of membership to museums and art related clubs and societies. Included are certificates of membership to the Allied Artists of America, the International Art-Union, NewYork Gallery of Fine Arts and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Also included is John McComb's 1816 membership certificate for the American Academy of Fine Arts; and a hand lettered certificate, given to Samuel T. Shaw by the Salmagundi Club, to commemorate the twenty-fifth anniversary of the Shaw Purchase Prize. Certificates from the National Academy of Design include those given to J. Carroll Beckwith, Asher B. Durand, and Helen M. Turner.
  - American Academy of the Fine Arts, 1816-1817 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Art Union, 1849 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1893, 1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Academy of Design, 1841-1937 (Folder FF1)
  - New-York Gallery of Fine Arts, 1827 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Salmagundi, 1928 (Folder FF1)
  - Society of Iconophiles, 1905 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Certificates presented to the New-York Historical Society, 1943-1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II. Business, 1889-1942
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes certificates issued by or to business organizations. Included is a certificate from the NY State Office of the Secretary of State granting Strobridge Lithographers a license to do business in New York. One certificate of note is a certificate of membership to the Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, given to General William T. Sherman in 1889. Another is a hand-lettered certificate presented to Edwin B. Moore upon his retirement from the New York Tribune. Of special interest is an 1893 certificate from Tiffany and Co. presented to Adalbert Emil Herrman Nordbrock upon completion of his apprenticeship in the silversmith department.
  - American Society of Certified Public Accountants, 1922 (Folder FF3)
  - New York City Mayor's Business Advisory Committee, 1942 (Folder FF2)
  - NY State Chamber of Commerce, 1889-1899 (Folder FF2)
  - NY State Office of the Secretary of State (business license), 1893 (Folder FF3)
  - Rice Leaders of the World Association, 1932 (Folder FF3)
  - Tiffany and Company, 1893 (Folder FF3)
- Series III: Celebrations and Events, 1852-1955
  This series contains certificates related to the planning, funding, and participation of a variety of expositions, fairs, events. Certificates include an invitation to the dedication ceremonies of the New York State Monument at Gettysburg in 1893, a blank certificate for the New England Sanitary Commission Fair in 1863, and a souvenir of the Civic & Industrial Parade, in New York City, 1889. Also included are certificates for the 1939 New York World's Fair and two certificates, designed and engraved by the Major & Knapp Co., for the United States Centennial Exhibition.
  A beautifully detailed and hand-colored certificate created by the Ancient Order of Hibernians, thanking William Sulzer for his participation in their St. Patrick's Day Celebration in Albany, 1894. Two certificates from the 1877 Agricultural Society of New South Wales' Metropolitan Intercolonial Exhibition awarded John Rogers bronze medals for his statuary. Certificates given to J. Carroll Beckwith commemorate his participation in the Universal Exposition in St. Louis, the Exposition Universell of 1900, the First International Exposition of Modern Decorative Arts in Turin, and the Louisiana Purchase Exposition. Asher B. Durand's certificate for engraving from the 1876 International Exhibition in Philadelphia is included as well. Certificates from the American Institute Fair are heavily illustrated and engraved by the American Bank Note Company.
  Of special note is an 1852 certificate issued by the Common Council of the City of New York announcing a public reception for Irish patriot Thomas Francis Meagher "in appreciation of his services in the cause of Civil Liberty."
  - Agricultural Society of New South Wales' Metropolitan Intercolonial Exhibition, 1877 (Folder FF57)
  - Alaska-Yukon-Pacific Exposition, 1909 (Folder FF4)
  - American Institute Fair, 1875, 1879 (Folder FF58)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians St. Patrick's Day Celebration, 1894 (Folder FF58)
  - Civic and Industrial Parade NYC, 1889 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Common Council of the City of New York Resolution for a Public Reception for Irish patriot Thomas Francis Meagher, 1852 (Folder FF58)
  - Cotton States and International Exposition, 1895 (Folder FF4)
  - Greater City of New York Anniversary (25th and 50th), 1923, 1948 (Folder FF4)
  - Flag Day Proclamation, 1955 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Louisiana Purchase Exposition, 1904 (Folder FF57)
  - Mardi Gras, 1912 (Folder FF4)
  - New England Sanitary Commission Fair, 1863 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York State Monument at Gettysburg, 1893 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York World's Fair, 1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sesquicentennial International Exposition, 1926 (Folder FF4)
  - United States International Centennial Exhibition, 1876 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  - United States International Centennial Exhibition, 1876 (Folder FF57)
  - Washington's Inauguration Centennial, 1889 (Folder FF4)
  - Washington's Inauguration Centennial, 1889 (Folder FF58)
  - World's Columbian Exhibition, 1890 (Folder FF4)
  - World's Columbian Exhibition, 1893 (Folder FF58)
  - World's Columbian Exhibition, 1893 (Folder Oversize FF 82)
- Series IV: Civic, 1778-1943
  This series includes commendations, membership, and professional certificates. Most were issued by fire and police departments
  One fire department certificate is a colorful lithograph printed by Currier and Ives. New York City Fire Department certificates include several engraved by Peter Maverick from a drawing by Archibald Robertson. Another certificate, a fireman's exemption from jury duty, has an 1829 ten cent piece attached. Other fire department certificates were isuued by Albany, Paterson, San Francisco, and Toledo departments.
  Police department certificates include appointments to various positions in the New York City and Morrisania departments as well as a membership certificate to the Police Endowment Fund Association. One 1896 certificate is signed by Theodore Roosevelt, then president of New York's Board of Police Commissioners. Certificates given to policemen to commemorate cases they helped solve are hand-lettered and illustrated. One of these has an albumen portrait of Elmira, NY Police Chief Levi D. Little attached.
  Membership certificates from the Committee of Vigilance of the City of San Francisco include several that once belonged to John Stoneacre Ellis. There is also a certificate heralding the appointment of Benjamin Crane to Superintendent of Central Park 1870.
  Certificates honoring retiring or resigning workers are particularly beautiful. A certificate recording the resignation of fireman Zophar Mills includes an albumen photograph of a fire engine. Another, given to Colonel J. Mayhew Wainwright upon his resignation as the Commissioner of the Westchester County Park Commission, is hand-lettered in the style of an illuminated manuscript. Also included are certificates for Columbus Ryan, George Rivet Van Namee, and John W. Chambers. An albumen photograph of John Chambers is included on his certificate.
  - Bronx Borough President, 1917 (Folder FF59)
  - City of New York Department of Public Parks, 1870 (Folder FF59)
  - Fire Departments-New York City-Manhattan, 1778-1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Fire Departments-New York City-Manhattan, 1808-1914, undated (Folder FF5-FF6)
  - Fire Departments-New York City-Manhattan, 1829-1893 (Folder FF60)
  - Fire Departments-New York City-Manhattan, 1859, 1864 (Folder Oversize FF 82)
  - Fire Departments-New York City-Brooklyn, Bronx, Queens, 1850-1901 (Folder FF7)
  - Fire Departments-New York City-Brooklyn, Bronx, Queens, 1829-1903, undated (Folder FF61)
  - Fire Departments-Cities other than New York, 1828-1858, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fire Departments- Cities other than New York, 1851-1863, undated (Folder FF62)
  - Police Departments-New York City, 1851-1929 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Police Departments-New York City, 1866-1918 (Folder FF8)
  - Police Departments-New York and other cities, 1879-1884 (Folder FF63)
  - NY State Public Service Commission, 1943 (Folder FF59)
  - San Francisco Committee of Vigilance, 1851, undated (Folder FF9)
  - Westchester County Parks Commission, 1936 (Folder FF59)
- Series V: Education, 1802-1951
  This series is comprised of certificates of merit, diplomas, and teaching certificates. The bulk of the merit certificates and grammar school diplomas came from public schools in New York City. Diplomas include those from Columbia University, Cooper Union, Eastman National Business College, Princeton University, Rutgers Female Institute, the University of Maine and Yale University. Many of these certificates were printed on parchment and have elaborate seals. Includes diplomas from a variety of colleges and universities.Other certificates include teacher certifications, course completion certificates for classes at Cooper Union, a certificate of apprenticeship from the New York State Board of Pharmacy, and membership certificates for the Free-School Society of New-York and the American University Popular Course of Home Reading. There are certificates to various clubs and organizations at Columbia University and Harvard University. Library certificates include two certificates of membership to the New York Society Library.
  - Certificates of Merit, 1868, 1876, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates of Merit (cased) from Mrs. Okill's Female Boarding School, 1847, 1854 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Certificates of Merit-Public Schools-Manhattan, 1822-1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates of Merit–Public Schools-Manhattan, 1822-1875 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Certificates of Merit–Public Schools-Brooklyn and the Bronx, 1864-1901 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Certificates of Merit-Public Schools-Manhattan, Brooklyn and the Bronx, 1855-1885 (Folder FF10)
  - Certificates of Merit-Grammar School for Boys, 1871-1881 (Folder FF11)
    Scope and Contents
    9 certificates: Rudolph Miller (School #34), Abram W. Applegate (#55), Fritz W. Schivensen (#16), Thomas Kelby (#19), and 5 to Victor Hugo Paltsits.
  - Certificates of Merit-Grammar School for Girls, 1857, 1875-1886 (Folder FF12)
  - Certificates of Merit-Roll of Honor, 1886, 1888 (Folder FF13)
  - Certificates of Merit–Unidentified Schools, 1820-1893 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Certificates of Merit–blank, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - Certificates-New York Free School Society, 1810, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
  - Diplomas-Primary and Secondary Schools, 1856-1903 (Folder FF14-FF15)
    Includes Albany Female Academy, Male Grammar Schools #4, 16, 34, 35, 39, Morrisania Public School, Van Norman Institute, Female Grammar Schools #4, 25, 37, 63, Waterbury (CT) Center School District High School, Lincoln Grammar School (San Francisco), Bradford Academy (Mass), Harlem Evening High School, Berkeley School, Wilson Union School, New York Common School diploma District #6 (Porter, NY), Wadleigh High School, Brooklyn Public School #11, New York City Dept of Education elementary schools, Long Island City Public Schools, Union Free School #2 (Williamsbridge, NY), New York Grammar School #89, New York Evening High School (to Victor Hugo Paltsits), Martin Grammar School (Boston).
  - Diplomas-Columbia University, 1802-1934 (Folder FF16-FF17)
  - Diplomas-Cooper Union, 1864-1904 (Folder FF18)
  - Diplomas-Harvard University, 1857-1906 (Folder FF19)
  - Diplomas-Normal College, 1873,1899 (Folder FF20)
  - Diplomas-Yale University, 1868-1907 (Folder FF21)
  - Diplomas-College and University-A-Z (small), 1870-1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - Diplomas-College and University-A-Z (large), 1858-1915 (Folder FF64)
  - Diplomas-College and University-A-G, 1865-1943 (Folder FF22)
  - Diplomas-College and University-H-P, 1884-1924 (Folder FF23)
  - Diplomas-College and University-R-Z, 1829-1942 (Folder FF24)
  - Diplomas-Seminary, 1869-1871 (Folder FF25)
  - Diplomas-Helen Marie Closs, 1910-1918 (Folder FF-26a)
    4 diplomas tracing Closs's education: New York City public school (P.S. 44 in Queens), 1910; Far Rockaway High School, 1914; College of New Rochelle, Sodality of the Blessed Virgin Mary, 1917; B.A., Curatore Collegii Novae Rupellae (College of New Rochelle), 1918.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of James Fitzgerald, 2018.
  - Library Membership Certificates, 1833, 1870 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
  - Teaching Certificates, 1852-1895, undated (Folder FF26)
- Series VI: Financial, 1840-1941
  This series contains bank notes, stocks and other financial documents. Bank notes include those for the Hungarian Fund and an uncut sheet of four bank notes from The Farmers Bank. New York stocks include stock in the Brooklyn Union Elevated Railroad, the Coney Island and Brooklyn Railroad Company, the New York Pier and Warehouse Company, the Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corporation and the Bennett Combined Automatic, and Manual Organ Company of New York. Many of these certificates are illustrated.
  Other financial documents include Confederate States of America coupon bonds, used to raise capital for the war effort; a copy, probably printed as an advertisement, of a life insurance policy for Robert E. Lee, issued by the State Mutual Life Insurance Company; and bonds issued by the City of New Orleans.
  - 367th Infantry Auditorium Bond, undated (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bennett Combined Automatic and Manual Organ Company Stock Certificate, circa 1880 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corporation Stock Certificate, 1924-1941 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Union Elevated Railroad Stock Certificate, 1899 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chicago, St. Paul and Fond du Lac Railroad Company Bond, 1857 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Coney Island and Brooklyn Railroad Company Stock Certificate, 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Confederate States of America Bonds, 1863-1864 (Folder FF27)
  - Facsimile of Bank of New York Warrant No. 1, undated (Folder FF27)
  - Farmer's Bank, circa 1840 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hungarian Fund, 1852 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - LaCrosse Gold Mining Company of Colorado, 1866 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - New England Protection Union Stock Certificate, 1852 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - New Orleans City Bonds, 1862 (Folder FF27)
  - New York Academy of Music Stock Certificate, 1885 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - New York Pier and Warehouse Company Stock Certificate, 1866 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Peanut Club Bond, 1880 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Philadelphia City Bond, 1874 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Port Royal and Augusta Railway Company Bond, 1878 (Folder FF27)
  - Southern California Home Builders Stock Certificate, 1913 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - State Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1906 (Folder FF27)
  - United States of Freedom Bond, 1895-1896 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Water Stock/Water Loan of the City of New York Certificates, circa 1840 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Foreign Language, 1852-1947
  This series includes certificates in Arabic, Dutch, Danish, French, Greek, Latin, Polish, Spanish, Italian and German. The certificates have not been translated but include religious, academic, and honorary subjects.
  Certificates in French are mainly honoring soldiers who served in World War I. One of these certificates of honor has the Chateau-Thierry Medal attached. The medal depicts the busts of Washington & Lafayette and the Legion of Honor on the reverse. A 1907 membership certificate records aviator Alan Hawley's membership in L'Aero-Club de France.
  - Arabic, undated (Folder FF28)
  - Danish, 1929 (Folder FF28)
  - Dutch, 1852, undated (Folder FF28)
  - French, 1907-1947 (Folder FF29)
  - German, undated (Folder FF28)
  - Greek, undated (Folder FF28)
  - Italian, 1871 (Folder FF28)
  - Latin, 1878-1922, undated (Folder FF28)
  - Polish, 1923-1937 (Folder FF28)
  - Spanish, 1880, 1889 (Folder FF28)
- Series VIII: Fraternal, 1792-1937
  This series includes certificates of membership to fraternal organizations and lodges including the Odd Fellows and the Freemasons. Freemason organizations represented include the Scottish Rite, the Police Square Club, and Knights Templar. Several certificates use the Masonic calendar, recording years in AL or AO. Many of these certificates are printed on parchment and have wax or embossed seals.
  The collection includes several certificates of membership, given to John Stoneacre Ellis, to both California Freemason and Odd Fellow organizations. A colorful lithograph, titled "Masonic Chart" and printed by Strobridge & Co., contains religious and symbolic imagery. A memorial certificate for Benjamin S. Clark records his history with the masons and includes an albumen portrait.
  - Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine for North America [Shriners], 1889, 1902 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Order of Druids, 1846 (Folder FF30)
  - Elks Lodge, 1868 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fraternal Order of Eagles, 1904 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fraternity of Delta Psi/ St. Anthony Hall, 1882 (Folder FF30)
  - Freemasons, 1808-1937 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Freemasons, 1853-1907 (Folder FF30)
  - Freemasons, 1886 (Folder FF65)
  - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, 1834 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, 1844 (Folder FF30)
  - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, 1858, 1864 (Folder FF65)
  - Knights Templar, 1864, 1890 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Knights Templar, 1863 (Folder FF30)
  - Mystic Order of Veiled Prophets of the Enchanted Realm, 1912 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Order of United Americans, 1848, undated (Folder FF65)
  - Society of Black Friars, 1792-1795 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Stuyvesant Club, 1869 (Folder Oversize FF 82)
- Series IX: Genealogical, 1785-1940
  This series is comprised of membership certificates to organizations that base their membership on lineage. Societies include the Daughters of the American Revolution, the Society of Colonial Wars, the Society of Mayflower Descendants, the Saint Nicholas Society of the City of New York, the Society of California Pioneers, the Society of the Cincinnati and Sherwood Kindred of America. Some of these certificates are printed on parchment and have original wax seals.
  - Association of Descendants of Andrew Ward, 1904 (Folder FF66)
  - American College of Heraldry and Genealogical Registry, 1878 (Folder FF66)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1902, 1905, 1931 (Folder FF31)
  - Genealogical Society of Pennsylvania, 1928 (Folder FF66)
  - Holland Society of New York, 1885-1937 (Folder FF32)
  - Huguenot Society of London, 1909 (Folder FF66)
  - Hyde Association, 1880 (Folder FF66)
  - Institute of American Genealogy, 1939 (Folder FF66)
  - National Society of Women Descendants of the Ancient and Honorable Artillery Company, 1931 (Folder FF66)
  - Order of the Founders and Patriots of America, 1911, 1924 (Folder FF33)
  - Saint Nicholas Society NYC, 1835-1894 (Folder FF67)
  - Sherwood Kindred of America, 1940 (Folder FF66)
  - Society of American Wars, 1911 (Folder FF66)
  - Society of Americans of Royal Descent, 1935 (Folder FF66)
  - Society of California Pioneers, 1859 (Folder FF68)
  - Society of the Cincinnati, 1785-1896, undated (Folder FF69)
  - Society of the Colonial Dames of America, 1900, 1926 (Folder FF34)
  - Society of the Colonial Wars, 1884-1922 (Folder FF70)
  - Society of the Daughters of 1812, 1903 (Folder FF66)
  - Society of Magna Charta Dames, 1935 (Folder FF66)
  - Society of Mayflower Descendants, 1923 (Folder FF71)
  - Society of the War of 1812, 1893-1918 (Folder FF66)
  - Sons of the Revolution, 1892, 1917-1918 (Folder FF72)
- Series X: Historical, 1823-1980
  This series is comprised mainly of certificates of membership and acknowledgements of financial contributions to organizations focused on commemorating various aspects of American history.
  Membership certificates include those to the American Antiquarian Society, the American Historical Association, the Massachusetts Historical Society, and the New-York Historical Society. New-York Historical Society membership certificates are illustrated with an image of the arrival of Henry Hudson, engraved by Asher B. Durand. Blank New-York Historical Society fellow and patron certificates include an original drawing of the certificate by its designer, E. D. French. Also included are certificates from the New Hampshire Historical Society, the American Flag House and Betsy Ross Memorial Association, and a number of presidential societies. The American Bank Note Company printed the certificates of membership for the Roosevelt Memorial Association and the Alexander Hamilton National Memorial Association.
  Acknowledgements of contributions include those to the Washington National Monument, the Bunker Hill Monument Association, and the National Lincoln Monument in Illinois, as well as a certificate acknowledging a donation to provide a pedestal for the Statue of Liberty.
  - American Antiquarian Society, 1940 (Folder FF39)
  - American Committee on the Statue of Liberty, 1883 (Folder FF34)
  - American Flag House and Betsy Ross Memorial Association, 1889-1913 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)